Guide to the Robert R. Wilson papers, 1936-2000.
Wilson, Robert R. papers, 1936-2000.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Robert R. Wilson papers, 1936-2000.
14-22-3093
Robert R. Wilson 1914-
12.9 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, correspondence, papers, talks, articles, clippings, notes and notebooks, course materials, memorabilia, professional papers, drawings, designs and photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Memorabilia documenting the development of atomic energy research and high energy physics in the United States, Europe, and Asia. Dr. Wilson was a renowned expert on designing and constructing cyclotrons and synchrotrons, serving as consultant on projects around the world. Included in his professional papers are drawings, designs and photographs of some of the buildings, accelerators and equipment he helped design, as well as some of his sculptures. Among the personal papers in the collection are some family letters, documents and photographs.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Robert Rathbun Wilson was born in 1914 in Frontier Wyoming, received an A.B. from the University of California, Berkeley, 1936, and after studying with Prof. Ernest O. Lawrence, a Ph.D. in 1940.
He participated in an early effort led by Enrico Fermi at Columbia University to build a nuclear reactor as part of a joint effort with Princeton University, where he was a lecturer and assistant professor, 1940-1942. He worked for Princeton University's reactor project, 1941-1942; becoming technical head of their isotope separation project, 1942-1943, and developing a uranium isotope-separating machine. He moved to Los Alamos Laboratory in 1943, one of the first to reside there, helping with early organization and formation of the Cyclotron Group, and becoming Head of the Research Division, 1944-1945. In 1945 he became Associate Professor of Physics at Harvard University where he designed the 150 MeV cyclotron and suggested radiological use of high-energy heavy particles for cancer therapy. He also worked on scattering of protons by protons to higher energies, using the cyclotron at the Radiation Laboratory at Berkeley, 1946-1947.
He came to Cornell University in 1947, working on building a series of electron synchrotrons, beginning with a 300 MeV machine and achieving 10 GeV in 1967. He and his colleagues made many discoveries regarding the inner structure of the proton including discovery of the first excited state of the proton and its next two excited states as well as scattering of electrons by protons. They were able to measure the production of K-mesons by X-ray beam. Dr. Wilson made the first measurement of the scattering of protons by the electric field of the nucleus of the atom, continuing this work while serving as Prof. d'Exchange at the University of Paris, France, in 1956. Also during his tenure at Cornell he conceived the idea to achieve the result of a high temperature in plasma by producing an imploding shock wave in an ionized gas through the sudden application of a strong magnetic field. He was one of the first to use the Monte Carlo method of mathematical computation, applying it to electron and proton initiated showers, invented the Quantometer to precisely measure the intensity of high-energy X-ray beams.
In 1967 he became first Director of Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab) in Batavia, Illinois. He held this position during its founding and assisted in the design and construction of the entire complex, which included a 500 GeV proton accelerator. The most notable of the approximately 250 experiments concerned interaction of neutrinos and muons at high energy and discovery of the "b quark." He also initiated to design and construction of the Tevatron, a system of superconducting magnets to raise the energy of the Fermilab synchrotron to one TeV (1000 GeV). In 1978 he was made Emeritus Director.
He then held the position of Peter B. Ritzma Professor at University of Chicago, 1978-1980, being named "Emeritus" in 1980. His then became I. I. Rabi Visiting Professor of Science and Human Relations at Columbia University in 1979; and the Michael Pupin Prof. at Columbia University, 1980-1982, becoming "Emeritus" in 1982.
During his career he assisted in the design and construction of cyclotrons and synchrotrons in the United States and Europe and participated in many international symposia relating to high energy physics. He became a member of the American Physical Society in 1938, president in 1985; helped found the Federation of American Scientists, Chairman in 1946 and 1963; was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1957, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1968, and the American Philosophical Society in 1969. He served on the Editorial Board of the magazine Daedalus. He was also affiliated with many other organizations having to do with teaching physics and high energy physics research, as well as arts and letters.
He received the Elliot Cresson Award in 1964, National Medal of Science in 1973, Enrico Fermi Award in 1984, del Gado Gold Medal of Radiology in 1989, and the Gemant Award in 1995. He has received honorary degrees from University of Notre Dame, Sci Dr 1969; North Central College, ScD 1975; University of Bonn, ScD 1978; Harvard University, Sci Dr 1986, and Wesleyan University, Sci Dr 1987. He co-authored, with Raphael Littauer, the book "Accelerators" published in 1958.
Dr. Wilson has been active in international physics attending numerous meetings including the conference organizing CERN, 1952, in Copenhagen; one of the earliest in the USSR, 1954; the Peoples Republic of China, 1974; meetings in New Orleans, 1975; Moscow, 1976; Hamburg, 1977; and Fermilab, 1978. He participated in the organization of the International Committee for Future Accelerators (ICFA), of which he was an American delegate.
While on sabbatic leave in Italy in 1961, Wilson studied sculpture at the Academia Belli Arte.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Manuscripts, correspondence (including many requests to give talks or seminars or advice on building accelerators), papers, talks, articles, clippings, notes and notebooks, course materials, photographs, and memorabilia documenting the development of atomic energy research and high energy physics in the United States, Europe, and Asia. Dr. Wilson was a renowned expert on designing and constructing cyclotrons and synchrotrons, serving as consultant on projects around the world. He was also highly regarded as a lecturer and teacher of physics and historian of world affairs relating to the developing uses of atomic energy. Included in his professional papers are drawings, designs and photographs of some of the buildings, accelerators and equipment he helped design, as well as some of his sculptures. Among the personal papers in the collection are some family letters, documents and photographs, as well as designs and plans for his homes in New Mexico and Florida.
Correspondents include: Len Ackland, J. B. Adams, Paul Aebersold, Samuel K. Allison, Luis Alvarez, Edoardo Amaldi, Robert Bacher, Kenneth T. Bainbridge, Charles Parker Baker, Gilberto Bernardini, Hans A. Bethe, Norris Bradbury, Gregory Breit, Morton Camac, James Cassels, Wen-yu Chang, Stirling Colgate, Alice Cook, Donald Cooksey, Dan Cooper, Robert Cornog, Dale R. Corson, L. S. Cottrell, Ed Creutz, Karl K. Darrow, John DeWire, Pierre Donzelot, Philippe Eberhard, Bernard Feld, Dennis Flanagan, William A. Fowler, Jerome H. Fregau, R. C. Gibbs, William T. Golden, Maurice Goldhaber, Edwin L. Goldwasser, L. Goldzahl, S. Goutsmit, Kenneth Greisen, T. C. Griffith, Gaylord P. Harnwell, W. W. Havens, Jr., David Hawkins, Leland J. Haworth, S. S. Hecker, William Higenbotham, Frederic de Hoffmann, Robert Hofstadter, Gerald Holton, David R. Inglis, W. K. Jentschke, Donald W. Kerst, Seishi Kikuchi, Raymond N. Knellberg, George A. Kolstad, James A. Krumhansl, Hirao Kumagai, L. Jackson Laslett, Ernest O. Lawrence, Leon M. Lederman, T. D. Lee, A. J. Leigh, J. S. Levinger, Maurice M. Levy, Urner Liddel, Raphael Littauer, M. Stanley Livingston, Edward J. Lofgren, Franklin A. Long, Harry Lustig, T. W. Mackesey, John H. Manley, Robert E. Marshak, Boyce D. McDaniel, Paul W. McDaniel, Edwin M. McMillan, J. Howard McMillen, Richard L. Meier, E. E. Minett, Philip Moon, Philip Morrison, Paul M. O'Leary, Frank Oppenheimer, J. Robert Oppenheimer, Jay Orear, Philip S. Owen, Wolfgang K. H. Panofsky, and Richard Parmenter.
Correspondents also include: Lyman G. Parratt, R. E. Peierls, James A. Perkins, F. Perrin, Melba Phillips, Bruno Pontecorvo, William Preston, Federico Quercia, Norman Ramsey, Leonard M. Rieser, Arthur Roberts, Thomas R. Rogers, Edward T. Rosenbaum, Arthur E. Ruark, Robert G. Sachs, Carl Sagan, Giorgio Salvini, Joseph Halle Schaffner, Herwig Schopper, Emilio Segráe, Frederick Seitz, R. S. Shankland, A. H. Shapley, Kai Siegbahn, Albert Silverman, Daniel M. Singer, Ralph Carlisle Smith, H. D. Smyth, Jack Steinberger, Jeremy J. Stone, Sandro Stringari, S. Cushing Strout, John M. Swomley, Leo Szilard, John T. Tate, Edward Teller, Emily Thompson, John S. Toll, Timothy E. Toohig, Robert L. Walker, Alvin M. Weinberg, Victor F. Weisskopf, John A. Wheeler, Harry J. White, Milton G. White, E. P. Wigner, Herman S. Wigodsky, Frederic H. Williams, John H. Williams, Robert Williams, Richard Wilson, Michael Witherell, William M. Woodward, T. P. Wright, William E. Wright, Chien Shiung Wu, Yuan Chia-liu, and A. Zichichi.
Tape recording and transcript of the Memorial Service for Robert R. Wilson, March 11, 2000.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wilson, Robert R.,1914-; Ackland, Len.; Adams, J. B.; Aebersold, Paul C.(Paul Clarence), 1910-1967.; Allison, Samuel King, 1900-1965.; Alvarez, Luis W., 1911-; Amaldi, Edoardo.; Amaldi, U.(Ugo), 1934-; Amrine, Michael.; Anderson, Herbert Lawrence.; Anderson, Roland.; Bacher, Robert F.(Robert Fox), 1905-; Bainbridge, Kenneth T.(Kenneth Tompkins), 1904-1996.; Baker, Charles Parker.; Bernardini, Gilberto.; Bethe, Hans Albrecht, 1906-; Blaisdell, Warren.; Bradbury, Norris.; Breit, Gregory.; Camac, Morton.; Cassels, James.; Chang, Wen-yu.; Colgate, Stirling.; Cook, Alice Hanson.; Cooksey, Donald.; Cooper, Dan.; Cornog, Robert.; Corson, Dale R.; Cottrell, L. S.; Creutz, Ed.; Darrow, Karl K.(Karl Kelchner), 1891-; DeWire, John.; Donzelot, Pierre.; Eberhard, Philippe.; Feld, Bernard Taub, 1919-; Flanagan, Dennis, 1919-; Fowler, William A.; Fregau, Jerome H.; Gibbs, R. C.; Golden, William T., 1909-; Goldhaber, Maurice, 1911-; Goldwasser, Edwin L.; Goldzahl, L.; Gomez, Ricardo J.(Ricardo Juan), 1935-; Greisen, Kenneth.; Griffith, T. C.; Harnwell, G. P.(Gaylord Probasco), 1903-1982; Hastie, John W.; Havens, W. W.; Hawkins, David, 1913-; Haworth, Leland J.(Leland John), 1904-; Higenbotham, William.; Hoffmann, Frederic de.; Hofstadter, Robert, 1915-; Holton, Gerald James.; Inglis, David Rittenhouse, 1905-; Jacob, Maurice.; Kerst, Donald W.; Kikuchi, Seishi, 1902-1974.; Kjellberg, Raymond N.; Kolstad, George A.; Krumhansl, James A.; Kumagai, Hirao.; Laslett, L. Jackson(Lawrence Jackson), 1913-; Lawrence, Ernest Orlando, 1901-1958.; Lederman, Leon M.; Lee, T. D., 1926-; Leigh, A. J.; Levinger, Joseph S., 1921-; Liddel, Urner.; Littauer, Raphael, 1925-; Livingston, M. Stanley(Milton Stanley); Lofgren, Edward J.; Long, Franklin A., 1910-; Lustig, Harry.; Mackesey, Thomas W.(Thomas William), 1908-1976.; Manley, John Henry, 1907-; Marshak, Robert Eugene, 1916-; McDaniel, Boyce D.(Boyce Dawkins), 1917-; McDaniel, Paul W.; McMillan, Edwin M.(Edwin Mattison), 1907-; McMillen, J. Howard.; Meier, Richard L.; Minett, E. E.; Moon, Philip.; Morrison, Philip.; O'Leary, Paul M.; Oppenheimer, Frank.; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967.; Orear, Jay.; Owen, Philip S.; Panovsky, Wolfgang K. H.; Parmenter, Richard.; Parratt, Lyman G.(Lyman George); Peierls, Rudolf Ernst, 1907-; Perkins, James A.; Perrin, F.; Phillips, Melba, 1907-; Pontekorvo, B.(Bruno), 1913-; Preston, William.; Quercia, Italo Federico.; Ramsey, Norman, 1915-; Rieser, Leonard M.; Roberts, Arthur.; Rogers, Thomas R.; Rosenbaum, Edward T.; Ruark, Arthur Edward, 1899-; Sachs, Robert Green, 1916-; Sagan, Carl, 1934-; Salvini, Giorgio.; Schaffner, Joseph Halle.; Schopper, Herwig F.; Segráe, Emilio.; Seitz, Frederick.; Shankland, Robert S., 1908-; Shapley, A. H.; Siegbahn, Kai, 1918-; Silverman, Albert.; Singer, Daniel M.; Smith, Ralph Carlisle, 1910-; Smyth, Henry De Wolf, 1898-; Steinberger, J.; Stone, Jeremy J.; Strickler, Thomas B.; Stringari, S.; Strout, S. Cushing,; Swomley, John.; Szilard, Leo.; Tate, John F.; Teller, Edward.; Thompson, Emily Ann.; Toll, John Sampson, 1923-; Toohig, Timothy E.; Walker, R. L.(Robert Lee), 1919-; Weinberg, Alvin Martin, 1915-; Weisskopf, Victor Frederick, 1908-; Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-; White, Harry J.(Harry James), 1905-; White, Milton G.; Wigner, Eugene Paul, 1902-; Wigodsky, Herman S.; Williams, Frederic H.; Williams, John H.(John Harry), 1908-; Williams, Robert, 1940 Oct. 14-; Wilson, Richard, 1926-; Witherell, Michael.; Woodward, William.; Wright, T. P.; Wright, William.; Wu, C. S.(Chien-shiung), 1912-; Yuan, Chia-liu.; Zichichi, Antonino.; Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory.; Los Alamos National Laboratory--Research division.; Manhattan Project.
Subjects:
Nuclear physics--Research.; Nuclear physics--Study and teaching.; Particle accelerators--Construction.; Particle accelerators--Research.; Particle accelerators--Study and teaching.; Physics.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 15: restricted to permission of the Archivist
Series List
Series I. Biographical
Series II. Correspondence
General/Professional
Series III. Professional Papers
Proposals
Drawings/Figures
Papers: Drafts, reprints, articles, clippings (by or mentioning R.R.W.)
Drafts, reprints, articles, clippings by others
Reports/Annual reports
Talks by or mentioning R.R.W.
Talks by Others
Contracts and agreements
Patents for inventions by R.R.W.
Patents for inventions by others
Calendars
Subject Files
Series IV. Professional Organizations
Organizational/Membership Documents
Memoranda/Announcements
Series V. Conferences/Seminars
Series VI. Newsletters, Press Releases
Newsletters
Press Releases
Series VII. Course Work
Notes/Data
Course Notes
Notebooks
Course Materials
Course Requirements/Outlines
Student Papers
Series VIII. Honors and Degrees
Series IX. Professional Miscellany
Membership/Mailing Lists
Travel expenses
Programs
Proposal Review
Miscellaneous Printed Material
Broadsides
Maps
Drawings by Others
Memorabilia
Audio Cassettes
Series X. Personal/Family
Obituaries
Correspondence
Genealogy
Legal Documents
Career/Employment
Scholarships
Consultancy/Guest Speaker/Committee Member
Employment offers
Financial matters
Poetry
Sketches
Health
Automobiles
Miscellaneous
Residences
Series XI. Visual Images
Photographs
Transparencies
Negatives
Slides
Video
Series XII. Miscellany
Memorabilia
Series XIII. Personel (RESTRICTED)
General Personnel
Individuals: letters of reference, inquiries about employment, etc.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical
  - Curriculum Vitae [8 tm], 1978-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical material [3 tm, 3 carbons, 5 photocopies]; form for Who's Who in America (completed) [phc], one with annotations [phc], 1957-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drafts and notes for autobiography [2 am, 1 tm], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Drafts for autobiography [1 tm, 3 am], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cornell Laboratory of Nuclear studies (LNS) reminiscences [1 phc, 1 cc], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fermilab notes [2 am, 2 pp. tm], 1968, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fermilab, drafts [1 p. am, 2 tm], n.d., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fermilab miscellaneous drafts [12 tm, 7 am, 1 phc], 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - L.A.N.L.: interview with Lillian Hoddeson [tm + annotations], 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "L.A.N.L., 1943-1945" [tm], 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10-15)
  - "Princeton, 1940-1942" [printed manuscript + annotations], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Princeton: memoirs, "Pacifist to Warrior" [printed manuscript + annotations], n.d., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Princeton: isotron [printed manuscript + annotations], 1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 2 reminiscences [phc + tm with annotations], 1963, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous notes [am, phc], 1956-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memorial service transcript and tape [1 tm, 1 audio cassette], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Angela Gonzales article [1 phc], 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Biographical Memoirs, Boyce McDaniel and Albert Silverman [1 phc], 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II. Correspondence - General/Professional
  - Abdelaziz, Ezzat, Arab Development Institute, to R.R.W., Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (NAL), re Conference on Nuclear Technology in Developing Countries--Problems and Prospects [tls]; reply from R.R.W., Los Alamos National Laboratory (L.A.N.L.), 8/18/1980 [phc]., n.d., 8/18/1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Abdelaziz, Mohamed E., Arab Development Institute, to R.R.W., Columbia University, re Conference on Nuclear Technology in Developing Countries [tls], 9/2/1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ableson, Phil to R.R.W., Cornell University (C. U.), re recently published book [tls]; reply from R.R.W., 7/12/1985 [als], 1/7/1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Abrahamson, James A., United States Air Force, to R.R.W., re directed energy weapons and classified information, 6/22/1985 [phc]; G. A. Keyworth, Science Advisor to the President, to Dr. C.K.K. Patel, American Physical Society (APS) Study on Directed Energy Weapons, 6/17/1985 [phc], 6/22/1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Abrams, Allen, Wausau, WI, to R.R.W., C.U., re NAM Research Committee meeting [tls], 12/12/1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Abrams, Professor, also professors Brown, Griffin, Laubengayer and Guerlac, C.U., to Chairmen of Departments, College of Arts and Sciences, C.U.B.A., re degree "with distinction" requirements [mc], 3/7/1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Abrams, M. H., Lamont Cole, Henry Guerlac, A. E. Kahn, H. F. Newhall, William F. Oechler, Robert Palmer, and Clinton Rossiter, C.U., to Dean Cottrell, C.U., re undergraduate education [mc], 5/25/1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Academic Press, Inc., from secretary to R.R.W., re paper entitled "Nuclear Radiation At Hiroshima and Nagasaki" [cc], 1/17/1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ackland, L[en], list of sequence of events development of atomic weapons [ams], 2/3/1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to Members of the Board of Sponsors, re moving the hands of the clock [tls], 9/20/1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to R.R.W., re draft memo about the clock [tls], 9/24/1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to R.R.W., re memo about the clock [tls], 9/24/1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, notes on previous Bulletin Clock changes [phc], 9/30/1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to Members of the Board of Sponsors, re Clock [phc], 9/30/1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to Board of Directors, re nuclear age issues [phc], 10/5/1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, from R.R.W., Board of Sponsors and Leonard M. Rieser, Board of Directors, re clock [phc], 12/19/1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ackland, Len, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, from R.R.W., Marathon, FL, re editorial "International Control of Nuclear Weapons: A Second Chance?" [als, tm, am], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Acosta, Julius Caesar C., Quezon City, Philippines, to R.R.W., Ithaca, NY, re science and religion [tls], 7/10/1996 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Elaine R., University News Bureau, C.U., to R.R.W., re Scientific American article [tls]; annotated copy of article [tm], 2/19/1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adams, J. B., CERN (Organization Européenne Pour La Recherche Nucléaire), to R.R.W., C. U., re parameters for C. U. synchrotron [tls], 11/24/1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adams, J. B., CERN, to R.R.W., C.U., containing invitations to CERN symposium [tls]; reply, 3/8/1956 [cc], 2/2/1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adams, J. B., CERN, to R.R.W., C.U., Conference on High Energy Acceleration and Instrumentation at CERN [tls], including invitation, questionnaire, and programme [tm]; reply [cc], 4/15/1959, 5/6/1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adams, J. B. Adams, ICFA (International Committee for Future Accelerators), to R.R.W., Columbia University, re meeting in July [tls], 4/28/1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adams, J. B. Adams, ICFA, to R.R.W., Columbia University, re meeting in July [tls], 5/13/1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adams, Robert M., C.U., from R.R.W., re "Institute for the Arts" [cc], 6/17/1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adams, Robert P., Michigan State College, to R.R.W., Princeton University, re meeting on the relationship between science and social progress today [tls], 11/7/1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adams, Ruth, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to R.R.W., Columbia University, re an article on scientific literacy [tls], 7/28/1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adams, Ruth, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to R.R.W., Columbia University, re welcoming him as a sponsor [tls], 4/4/1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adams, Ruth, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to R.R.W., Ithaca, NY, re his agreeing to be Chairman of the Bulletin's Board of Sponsors [tls], 9/30/1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adams, Ruth, The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, to R.R.W., Ithaca, NY, re moving the hands of the Bulletin clock [tls], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adkins, John N., Western Geophysical Company, to R.R.W., re press release (not attached) [tls], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Adler, Judy, N.Y.S. College of Home Economics, to R.R.W.: thank you for seminar participation [tls], 4/21/1964 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Aebersold, Paul C., University of California, Berkeley (UCB), to "Dear Fellows," re lab news and annual Christmas party [cc], 12/9/1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Aebersold, Paul C., UCB, to R.R.W., Princeton, re reports and security [tls]; note from Reg Richardson on verso [als], 10/14/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Aebersold, Paul C., UCB, to R.R.W., Princeton, re reports [tls], 10/16/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Aebersold, Paul C., UCB, to R.R.W., Princeton, re articles and reports [tls], 10/29/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Aebersold, Paul C., UCB, from R.R.W., "secret," re reports [cc], 11/11/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Agnew, Beverly and Harold, to "Jane and Bob," season's greetings [fax], 5/28/1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ahlfeldt, Elizabeth H., University of Rochester, from R.R.W., re Conference on High Energy Physics [cc], 1/19/1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Albertoni, Ettore A., Centro Studi Romagnosi, to R.R.W., C.U., re paper on Romagnosi [tls], 11/16/1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Albertson, R. D., (L.A.N.L.), to R.R.W., C.U., re Visiting Staff Member Agreement [tls], 6/10/1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Alikhanian, Marins, Armenian SSR Academy of Sciences, to R.R.W., C. U.: New Year wishes (telegram) [phc]; reply 1/3/1966 [typed telegram message], 1/2/1966 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Alikhanian, Marins, Armenian SSR Academy of Sciences, to R.R.W., New Year wishes [als], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Alikhanian, Marins, Armenian SSR Academy of Sciences, to R.R.W., C.U., New Year wishes [als], [1986?] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Al-Kilani, Sami Muhammed Salim: R.R.W., APS, to Prof. Yidzhak Zamir, Ministry of Justice, Jerusalem, re plight of Mr. Kalani [phc], 12/27/1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Allen, Harry S., to Major E. A. White, re moving cyclotron in Building X [cc], 12/5/1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Allen, Harry, from R.R.W., re equipment sent to Berkeley [cc], 1/21/1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Allen, Harry, from R.R.W., re broken quartz fiber microbalance [cc], 2/8/1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)